"The Best Sleeping Position for
Glymphatic Flow in the Brain"
Other than getting enough sleep,
what can we do to improve
the glymphatic clearance
of waste from our brains?
The provision
of a running wheel,
so mice could
voluntarily exercise,
has been shown to improve
glymphatic clearance
in aging mice,
which was accompanied
by a reduced buildup
of amyloid deposits
and improved cognition.
Sleeping position
may also make a difference.
Studies on rats show that
their natural sleeping position,
curled up on their sides,
allows for better
glymphatic transport
than sleeping on their backs
or stomachs.
People also tend
to spend most of their time
sleeping on their side,
particularly their right side
versus left,
compared to their backs
or stomachs.
This may maximize blood outflow
from the brain.
When we sleep
on our right side,
our right internal jugular vein,
the main blood vessel
in our neck
draining blood from the head,
is wide open,
and our left jugular
is partially collapsed
and vice versa.
Since most people have
a dominant right jugular vein,
sleeping on our right side
might maximize brain drainage.
Does it matter?
Well, people with
neurodegenerative disease,
mostly mild cognitive impairment
and Alzheimer's disease,
tend to sleep more
on their backs
than those
with normal cognition.
About seventy-two percent
spent at least two hours a night
on their backs compared
to 37 percent of those
with healthier brains,
raising
"the intriguing possibility
that head position
during sleep
could influence the clearing
of neurotoxic proteins
from the brain."
In crib death,
sudden infant death syndrome,
sleeping position
can be a life-saver,
leading to slogans like
"back to sleep,"
or more morbidly,
"face up to wake up."
It's premature
for an adult jingle,
maybe, on your flank
to not draw a blank?
The characteristic position
of poor sleepers
is on their back, though,
so maybe it's the poor sleeping
rather than the position,
per se,
that leads to cognitive decline,
or the causality
could be reversed,
with dementia deteriorating
good sleep habits.
Even if sleeping position
did matter,
it may take a night
in a sleep lab
to track your movements.
It turns out self-reported
sleep positions are often false.
Should brain benefits to side
sleeping ever be established,
you can train yourself with
so-called "positional therapies"
such as
the "tennis ball technique,"
which involves wearing a shirt
to bed backwards,
with a ball stuffed
in the chest pocket.
The uncertainties don't end
with sleeping position.
The glymphatic mechanism itself
was rapidly embraced
in scientific circles
and the popular press,
however,
it's been controversial.
It wasn't until 2019
that the first evidence
was published
that the glymphatic system
discovered in rodents
even existed in human brains.
Even the relationship between
sleep and Alzheimer's disease
is perhaps best summed up
in a recent neurology review
entitled "It's complicated."
Yes, those getting
less than 7 hours of sleep
may have higher rates
of Alzheimer's,
but those getting more than 8
are at higher risk too.
If anything,
population studies show
that longer sleep durations,
more than 8 or 9 hours,
are more strongly linked
to Alzheimer's disease
and dementia in general
than sleeping less than
5 or 6 hours.
The association between dementia
and long sleep duration
could be reverse causation,
where prodromal changes
in the brain
years before
Alzheimer's is diagnosed
causes prolonged sleep.
Long sleep duration may also
just be a confounding factor,
a marker of some
underlying health problem
that's the real culprit.
For example, oversleeping
may be a sign of depression,
which itself is an established
risk factor for dementia.
But there is a plausible
biological mechanism
for how extended sleep duration
could increase
dementia risk directly.
Longer sleep duration,
typically defined as sleeping
more than 8 hours a night,
is associated with signs
of systemic inflammation,
elevated levels of C-reactive
protein and Interleukin 6,
and both of those
inflammatory markers
in turn are associated with
an increase in dementia risk.
So much more
needs to be teased out
about the role
of the glymphatic system
before we make conscious efforts
to tweak it.